<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag:vimium | Pearls in Life]]></title>
  <link href="http://jhshi.me/tag/vimium/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jhshi.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-05T14:19:28-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jhshi.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jinghao Shi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vimium Not Working in Google Search Results Page]]></title>
    <link href="http://jhshi.me/2013/03/15/vimium-not-working-in-google-search-results-page/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T02:50:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jhshi.me/2013/03/15/vimium-not-working-in-google-search-results-page</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you're Vim user, then you must try <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/vimium/dbepggeogbaibhgnhhndojpepiihcmeb?hl=en">Vimium</a>. It makes your browsing
much much comfortable!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>These days, I found that Vimium commands (<code>j</code>, <code>k</code>, <code>f</code>) don't work on Google search
results page. But works just in in any other pages. I tried turning the instant
search off, logging out my account in Google's homepage, turning of personalized
search results, etc. None of those work.</p>

<p>Then I found that Vimium only stop working if I use Chrome's Omnibox to search.
That is, if I do the search in Google's home page instead of Chrome's Omnibox,
then everything is fine. I suspect that some extra flags in Omnibox's default
search pattern is the reason why Vimium refused to work.</p>

<p>But Omnibox is so convenience to use (<code>Alt+D</code> to focus &amp; search). Opening
Google's homepage every time you need search will certainly be another pain. So
I changed the default behavior of Chrome's Omnibox. Unfortunately, the built-in
Google search pattern is unchangeable, so I added an new search engine entry
and set it as default. Here is the fields of the new entry:</p>

<p><code>
Name: Google (or whatever you want)
Keyword: Google (or whatever you want)
Search Pattern: http://www.google.com/search?q=%s
</code></p>

<p>Here is a more detailed information about Google's search URL. Add whatever you
need, but keep it minimal, in case you screwed up with Vimium again :-)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.blueglass.com/blog/google-search-url-parameters-query-string-anatomy/">http://www.blueglass.com/blog/google-search-url-parameters-query-string-anatomy/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
