<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag:swap | Pearls in Life]]></title>
  <link href="http://jhshi.me/tag/swap/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jhshi.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-05T14:19:28-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jhshi.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jinghao Shi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OS161 Swapping]]></title>
    <link href="http://jhshi.me/2012/04/28/os161-swapping/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T13:27:39-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jhshi.me/2012/04/28/os161-swapping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that you can <a href="/2012/04/24/os161-physical-page-management">allocate/free physical pages</a>, and you have <a href="/2012/04/27/os161-tlb-miss-and-page-fault">demand paging
through handling TLB miss</a>. Let's get the final part work: swapping.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Three basic operations for a physical page</h3>

<p>The first is called <strong>evict</strong>. In a nutshell, <code>evict</code> a physical page means we
modify the page table entry so that this page is not Present (<code>PTE_P</code>), but
Swapped (<code>PTE_S</code>). And we also need to shoot down the relative TLB entry. But in
<code>evict</code>, we will not write the page's content to disk. Apparently, <strong>evict can
only operate on clean pages</strong>.</p>

<p>The second operation is <strong>swapout</strong>. We first write this page's content to
disk, which makes the page from dirty to clean. And the we just evict it.
<strong>swapout operation is for dirty pages</strong>.</p>

<p>The last operations is <strong>swapin</strong>. Basically, it's for read some virtual page
from swap file and place it in some physical page, and also need to modify
the relevant page table entry, making this page Present (<code>PTE_P</code>) instead of
Swapped(<code>PTE_S</code>).</p>

<h3>How to store the swapped pages</h3>

<p>We have two options here: store the pages in a <strong>disk</strong>, or in a <strong>file</strong>.</p>

<p>By default, sys161 provide two disks through lamebus, i.e., <code>lhd0</code> and <code>lhd1</code>. If
you want to store the pages in the raw disk, you should open the swap space like
this:</p>

<p>```c
struct vnode* swapfile;
int err = vfs_open("lhd0raw:", O_RDWR, 0, &amp;swapfile);
if (err != 0) {</p>

<pre><code>return err;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Note that the file name must be <code>lhd0raw:</code> or <code>lhd1raw</code> and the open flag must
be <code>O_RDWR</code>, since the disk is there, and needn't to be created or trunked.</p>

<p>On the other hand, if you decided to just store the pages in a normal file, then
you probably want to create the file like this:</p>

<p>```c
struct vnode* swapfile;
int err = vfs_open("swapfile", O_RDWR|O_CREAT|O_TRUNC, 0, &amp;swapfile);
if (err != 0) {</p>

<pre><code>return err;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>The file name is arbitrary, just choose one you like. And we provide the
<code>O_TRUNC</code> flag so that we got a "clean" swap file that contains no contents.
Then the file will be created under the root directory.</p>

<p>From my experience, store pages in normal file could be two times faster in
terms of read/write bandwidth.</p>

<p>For the same reason why we can not open consoles in <code>thread_create</code>, you can not
do this in <code>vm_bootstrap</code> since at that point, VFS system
was not initialized yet (see <code>$OS161_SRC/kern/startup/main.c</code> for boot sequence,
especially line 125~130). But it's OK, we can <strong>open the file until we really
need to write pages</strong>, e.g., when we swap out the first page.</p>

<p>We'll leverage the file operation to manipulate swapped pages. You may want to
review the file operation system calls to get familiar with VFS operations. We
use a lot <code>uio_kinit</code> and <code>VOP_READ</code>/<code>VOP_WRITE</code> here. But before all these, we need
to first create a swap file.</p>

<p>We also need some data structure to record each page's location in the swap
file. This data structure should be something like a map. The key is (address
space, va) pair, and the value is the location of the page. As usual, for
simplicity, we can just use a statically allocated array. <strong>Each array element
contains the (address space, va) pair, and this element's index is the page's
location</strong>. Of course, we need to set up a limit of maximum swapped page number
if we adopt this silly manner. When swap out a page, we first look up this
array (by comparing <code>as</code> and <code>va</code>) and find out if the swap file has already
contain a copy of this page, if yes then we directly overwrite that page and if
no, we just find a available slot and write the page to that slot.</p>

<p>A important note is that you want to <strong>create ONE swap file for all process</strong>,
instead of one swap file for each process. Since by doing the later, you also
have to allocate a mapping structure for each process and you'll run out of
memory very quickly (kernel pages are fixed, right?). Now the swap file and the
mapping data structure is a shared resource among all processes. So you need to
protect them with a lock.</p>

<h3>Two I/O operations on the swap file</h3>

<p>These two operations is quite straightforward. The first is called <code>write_page</code>,
which is responsible to <strong>write a page content to a specified location of the
swap file</strong>. The second is <code>read_page</code>, which is to <strong>read a specified page in
the swap file and copy the content to a physical page</strong>. We do not necessarily
have to have these to util functions but it's always good to abstract low level
operations and encapsulate to a convenient interface.</p>

<h3>The Swapping Work flow</h3>

<p>In your paging algorithm, you certainly will first look for free physical
pages. But once you fail to find such a page, you have to swap some page out
to get a free page. That's what the magic function <code>MAKE_PAGE_AVAIL</code> do in
<a href="/2012/04/24/os161-physical-page-management">my previous post about physical page allocation</a>.</p>

<p>Now let's take a look at the magic function. Denote the page that was to
swapped out as victim. If it's state is <code>PAGE_STATE_CLEAN</code>, it means that this
page already have a copy in disk and was not ever modified since swapped in. So
we can safely discard it's content. We use the <code>evict</code> operation to deal with it.
And after that, this page is available.</p>

<p>If this page is dirty, which means either this page do not have a copy in swap
file or this page was modified since it's swapped in, in both case, we need to
write its content to swap file. We can use the <code>swapout</code> operation here.</p>

<p>In <code>vm_fault</code> with fault type <code>VM_FAULT_READ</code> or <code>VM_FAULT_WRITE</code>, when we find that
this page is not Present (<code>PTE_P</code>), instead of allocate a new page for it, we
need to further check if this page was swapped (<code>PTE_S</code>), if yes then we need to
swap it in, if no then we can allocate a new physical page for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
